# NAIMUL HOQUE

email nhoque@umd.edu

website https://naimulhoque.github.io

#### RESEARCH INTEREST

My broad research interests are Human-Computer Interaction, Data Visualization, and Human-Centered AI. More specifically, I study how data visualization can help us to design AI-infused supertools, applications that amplify, augment, empower, and enhance human performance, by combining user experiences with AI support services. I argue that interactive visualization can work as a communication medium between humans and AI and help us retain human agency and ownership in AI-infused supertools.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2020–Present Research Assistant, University of Maryland,

College Park

MD, USA Human-Computer Interaction Lab (HCIL), Advisor: Niklas Elmqvist

Focus: Creativity support tools, accessible data visualization

May-Aug Research Intern, Bosch Research

2021

Virtual Advisor: Liang Gou

Focus: Interactively labeling large-scale image datasets

2018–2020 Research Assistant, Stony Brook University

NY, USA Advisor: Klaus Mueller

Focus: Creativity support tools, interactive causal inference

EDUCATION

2020-2024

(Expected) University of Maryland, College Park

MD, USA Ph.D. in Information Studies

2018-2020 Stony Brook University

NY, USA M.S. in Computer Science

2018-2020 University of Dhaka

Dhaka, Bangladesh B.Sc. in Computer Science

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# **Preprints**

Md Naimul Hoque, Tasfia Mashiat, Bhavya Ghai, Cecilia Shelton, Fanny Chavelier, Kari Kraus, Niklas Elmqvist. The HaLLMark Effect: Supporting Provenance and Transparent Use of Large Language Models in Writing with Interactive Visualization. *Under review*, 2024. https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13057

P2 Md Naimul Hoque, Ayman A Mahfuz, Mayukha Kindi, Naeemul Hassan.

Towards Designing a Question-Answering Chatbot for Online News:

Understanding Questions and Perspectives. *Under review*, 2024.

# Journal Publication

- J1 Shahreen Salim Aunti, Md Naimul Hoque, Klaus Mueller. Belief Miner: A Methodology for Discovering Causal Beliefs and Causal Illusions from General Populations. *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction (CSCW)*, 2024. (to appear)
- J2 Md Naimul Hoque, Niklas Elmqvist. Dataopsy: Scalable and Fluid Visual Exploration using Aggregate Query Sculpting. IEEE Transaction on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG), 2023. https://doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2023.3326594
- J3 Md Naimul Hoque, Wenbin He, Shekar Arvind Kumar, Liang Gou, Liu Ren. Visual Concept Programming: A Visual Analytics Approach to Injecting Human Intelligence at Scale. *IEEE Transaction on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG)*, 2022. https://doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2022.3209466
- J4 Md Naimul Hoque, Klaus Mueller. Outcome-Explorer: A Causality Guided Interactive Visual Interface for Interpretable Algorithmic Decision Making.

  IEEE Transaction on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG), 2021.

  https://doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2021.3102051
- J5 Md Naimul Hoque, Nazmus Saquib, Syed Masum Billah, Klaus Mueller.

  Toward Interactively Balancing the Screen Time of Actors Based on Observable
  Phenotypic Traits in Live Telecast. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer
  Interaction (CSCW), 2020. https://doi.org/10.1145/3415225

# Conference Publication

- C1 Md Naimul Hoque, Bhavya Ghai, Kari Kraus, Niklas Elmqvist. Portrayal:

  Leveraging NLP and Visualization for Analyzing Fictional Characters.

  Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS), 2023.

  https://doi.org/10.1145/3563657.3596000
- C2 Md Naimul Hoque, Md Ehtesham-Ul-Haque, Niklas Elmqvist, Syed Masum Billah. Accessible Data Representation with Natural Sounds. *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)*, 2023. https://doi.org/10.1145/3544548.3581087
- C3 Md Naimul Hoque, Bhavya Ghai, Niklas Elmqvist. DramatVis Personae:

  Visual Text Analytics for Identifying Social Biases in Creative Writing.

  Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS), 2022.

  https://doi.org/10.1145/3532106.3533526
- C4 Md Naimul Hoque, Choudhury Farhan Ahmed, Nicolas Lachiche, Carson K. Leung, Hao Zhang. Reframing in Clustering. *IEEE 28th International Conference on Tools with Artificial Intelligence (ICTAI)*, 2016.

# Workshop, Posters, and Extended Abstracts

- W1 Md Naimul Hoque, Niklas Elmqvist. Augmenting Human-AI Co-Writing with Interactive Visualization. In2Writing Workshop, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2023. https://naimulh0que.github.io/docs/In2Writing2023.pdf
- E1 Bhavya Ghai, Md Naimul Hoque, Klaus Mueller. WordBias: An Interactive Visual Tool for Exploring Intersectional Social Biases Encoded in Word Embeddings. Extended Abstracts of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2021. https://doi.org/10.1145/3411763.3451587
- W2 Md Naimul Hoque, Niklas Elmqvist. 2021. Towards Using Visual Analytics to Promote Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion. Workshop on Artificially Intelligent Technology for the Margins, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2021.
- P1 Md Naimul Hoque, Darius Coelho, Klaus Mueller. Examining the

Visualization Practices of Data Scientists on Kaggle. *IEEE VIS Poster*, 2019. https://naimulh0que.github.io/docs/Kaggle\_Analysis.pdf

Md Mehedi Hassan, Ashik Adnan, Asif M. Saleheen, Md Naimul Hoque. Understanding the Patterns of Crime Reports in a Popular Bangladeshi Newspaper. *Companion of ACM CSCW*, 2019. https://doi.org/10.1145/3272973.3274062

W3 Md Naimul Hoque, Rawshan E. Fatima, Manash Mandal, Nazmus Saquib.

Evaluating gender portrayal in Bangladeshi TV. Machine Learning for the

Developing World, NIPS, 2017. https://arxiv.org/pdf/1711.09728.pdf

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Fall 2023 Instructor, University of Maryland, College Park

MD, USA Sole instructor for the graduate-level Data Visualization course

2020–2022 Teaching Assistant, University of Maryland,
College Park

MD, USA Courses: Data Visualization, Data Science, Big Data Analysis

2018–2019 Teaching Assistant, Stony Brook University

NY, USA Courses: Data Structure, Data Science

2015–2018 Lecturer, Eastern University

Dhaka, Bangladesh Courses: Introduction to Programming, Data Structure, Algorithms

### INVITED TALKS

London, UK May 2023 · giCentre, City, University of London

Title: Supporting Complex Creative Writing Tasks with AI-Infused

Visualization

MD, USA April 2023 · HCIL Symposium, University of Maryland

Title: Supporting Complex Creative Writing Tasks with AI-Infused

Visualization

Toronto, CA Feb 2023 · DGP lab, University of Toronto

Title: Supporting Complex Creative Writing Tasks with AI-Infused

Visualization

MD, USA April 2021 · HCIL Symposium, University of Maryland

Title: Toward Interactively Balancing the Screen Time of Actors Based on

Observable Phenotypic Traits in Live Telecast

#### AWARDS AND HONORS

MD, USA 2023 · Doctoral Student Research Award (\$1000)

MD, USA 2021 · Doctoral Student Research Award (\$1000)

MD, USA 2021 · Dr. Dana Rotman Doctoral Student Travel Awards (\$500)

NY, USA 2018 · Chairman's Fellowship (\$3000), SBU

# SERVICES

Reviewer 2023 · ACM CHI, ACM DIS, IEEE VIS

2022 · ACM CHI, ACM DIS, IEEE VIS, ACM CSCW

2021 · ACM CHI, IEEE VIS, ACM CSCW

2020 · ACM CHI, ACM CSCW

Mentor Shahreen Salim · CS Ph.D., Stony Brook University

AYMAN MAHFUZ · High school student, now at UT Austin

Organizer 2023 · UMD HCIL Symposium

2022  $\,\cdot\,\,$  Maryland State Department of Education's workshop on creating an

accessible Data Science course for highschools.

December 7, 2023